<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE document PUBLIC "-//APACHE//DTD Documentation V1.2//EN" "document-v12.dtd">
<document> 
  <header> 
    <title>Welcome to telnetd2!</title>
    <version>@version@ (@date@)</version>
    <authors>
      <person name="Dieter Wimberger" email=" wimpi@users.sourceforge.net "/>
    </authors>
  </header> 
  <body> 
    <section>
      <title>About</title>
      <p>
      telnetd is an Open Source effort to implement a Java telnet daemon 
      that is compact and generic and thus easily embeddable into other applications.
      </p>
      <note>
      telnetd2 is an "update" of the last release to newer Java standards (will require >=1.4). 
      Please see the changes for more information. telnetd2 should compile and run under Java 5, which
      is probably not the case for the last release.
      </note>
      <note>
      telnetd2-osgi is a new branch that is designed to be used as OSGi bundle.
      </note>
      <p>
      Main Features are:
      </p>
      <ul>
        <li>Telnet protocol implementation (following specifications, support for NVT, ECHO, TTYPE, NAWS, LINEMODE,NEWENV)</li>        
        <li>Terminal I/O with support for various terminal types</li>
        <li>Simple UI toolkit as OO layer on top of the basic terminal I/O (work progress)</li>
        <li>Connection management (host based access and handling of idle connections)</li>
        <li>SSH Listener</li>
      </ul>
      <p>
        Main focus is a design that is flexible and powerful, yet at the same time stable
        and with a small runtime footprint. Threads required are two system threads per listener, 
        as well as one per connection.
      </p> 
    </section>
    <section>
       <title>Target Audience</title>
       <p>
       Developers that want to integrate reasonable telnet and SSH 2 access into their application.
       </p>
    </section>
    <note>This project is free and open source and this will not change in the future.
However, working on the project requires resources (beyond the ones provided
by SF). If you are willing to support the project financially, you are welcome
to make donations (via SF/PayPal).<br/>
Donated money will be used to pay Internet provider bills, provide and maintain
network facilities, enhance computing power and memory capacity. 5% will automatically   
be transfered to SF.net, for providing the hosting facilities on SF.</note>
  </body>
</document>
